A Finding Aid to the Mary Ann Scherr Papers, 1941-2007, bulk 1960-2000, in the Archives of American Art AAA.schemary
Archives of American Art
Mary Ann Scherr papers
bulk 1960-2000
1941-2007
AAA.schemary
Archives of American Art
2 Linear feet
The papers of jeweler and designer Mary Ann Scherr measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1941 to 2007, with the bulk of the material from 1960 to 2000. Scherr’s career is documented through scattered biographical material; correspondence with museums, universities, professional entities, and colleagues; writings by her as well as professional and student writings about her; business records documenting projects and connections with institutions and organizations; news clippings, promotional ephemera, catalogs, posters, and other printed materials; and photographs of Scherr and of her artwork.
Scherr, Mary Ann, 1931-
Scope and Contents note
The papers of jeweler and designer Mary Ann Scherr measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1941 to 2007, with the bulk of the material from 1960 to 2000. Scherr’s career is documented through scattered biographical material; correspondence with museums, universities, professional entities, and colleagues; writings by her as well as professional and student writings about her; business records documenting projects and connections with institutions and organizations; news clippings, promotional ephemera, catalogs, posters, and other printed materials; and photographs of Scherr and of her artwork.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Mary Ann Scherr conducted by Mary Douglas, April 6-7, 2001.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated by Mary Ann Scherr in 2001, 2005 and 2008 under the Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information. Use of video recording requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
Mary Ann Scherr (1921-) is a jeweler and designer living in Raleigh, North Carolina. Scherr was born in Akron, Ohio, and trained at the Cleveland Institute of Art, The University of Akron, and Kent State University, among others. She has worked in illustration, automotive and toy design, fashion, and metalwork but is most renowned for her functional approach to jewelry design through “body monitors,” high-tech utilitarian ornaments that monitor and react to the conditions of the wearer or the wearer’s surroundings.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1948-2005 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1941-2007 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 3: Writings, 1979-2005 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1947-2004 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1950-2007 (Box 1-2; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1960-1999 (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America; Goldsmiths--North Carolina--Raleigh; Jewelers--North Carolina--Raleigh; Jewelry making; Photographs; Women artists
- Biographical Material, 1948-2005; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains scattered biographical documents. Found here are awards and certificates; documents regarding Scherr’s interactions with government entities, including a video-recorded Governor’s Award interview on DVD; and family papers with photographs, news clippings, and brief resumes.
  - Awards, 1960s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Citizenship, 1960s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Governor's Award Interview, 2005; 1 Electronic discs (DVD) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scherr Family: Mary Ann Scherr, circa 1965-2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Scherr Family: Samuel Scherr, 1948-2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Scherr Family: Randall Scherr, 1965-2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Scherr Family: Sydney Scherr, 1954-2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scherr Family: Scott Scherr, 1952-2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Scherr Family: General, 1950s-2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1941-2007; Series 2; 5 Folders Box 1
  This series includes correspondence regarding special projects, exhibitions, and awards. Personal correspondence is comprised of congratulatory and anecdotal messages from friends and colleagues. Professional correspondence includes communications with museums, universities, and professional societies regarding art sales, submissions, and exhibitions.
  - Correspondence Regarding Body Monitors, 1973-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence Regarding Torch Shield, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1941-2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Professional Correspondence, 1962-2007 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
- Writings, 1979-2005; Series 3; 2 Folders Box 1
  Writings include a book manuscript and academic paper by Scherr as well as student essays, academic papers, and an award nomination essay about the artist.
  - Writings By Mary Ann Scherr, 1979-2005 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writings About Mary Ann Scherr, 1980-2002 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Personal Business Records, 1947-2004; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Personal Business Records contains documents pertaining to Scherr’s business activities, including news clippings, brochures, bulletins, collection records, correspondence, notes, illustrations, and images of art from projects with universities, professional groups, and museums. Most illustrations are photocopies, but there are some ink, graphite, and colored pencil original illustrations of jewelry as well.
  - Academic Associations, 1980s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - ALCOA, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Commissions, 1963-1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Design Projects, 1956-1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Industry Associations, 1976-2004 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Museum Collections, 1979-1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Patents and Legal, 1977-2004 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Permanent Collections, circa 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Project Illustrations: Books, 1955; 1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Project Illustrations: Jewelry, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Project Illustrations: Miscellaneous, 1947-1990s (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1970s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Smithsonian: Renwick Gallery, 1980s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Smithsonian: Science/History, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - United States Steel, 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Printed Material, 1950-2007; Series 5; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  This series includes photocopied book excerpts; a pack of craft-themed playing cards from the 2006 North Carolina Craft Exhibition; exhibition mailings and publicity materials; exhibition catalogs; professional journals and magazines in which Scherr is featured; clippings from newspapers, magazines, and web articles regarding the artist and her work; exhibition and event posters; two sales catalogs and one auction catalog; and printouts of web searches on the artist from a variety of years.
  - Book Excerpts, 1975-2002 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
  - Discover Craft NC Knowledge Cards, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Invitations, Brochures, 1963-2007 (Box 1, Folder 37-39)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1961-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
  - Journals and Magazines, 1978-2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, 1950-2000 (Box 2, Folder 10-15)
  - News Clippings on Body Monitors, circa 1970s-1990 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - News Clippings on Cookie Jar, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - News Clippings on Fashion/Style, 1956-1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - News Clippings on Foreign Exhibitions, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Posters, 1963-2000 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Sales and Auction Catalogs, 1982-1998 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Website Printouts, 1995-2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Photographs, circa 1960-1999; Series 6; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2
  Photographs of Mary Ann Scherr include two formal portraits of the artist, one photograph of the artist at work, one photograph of the artist in her studio, and one photograph of the artist during her Today Show interview in 1985. Photographs of artwork consist of images of Scherr’s jewelry on models or standing alone. Also found is one sheet of slides of artwork.
  - Photographs of Mary Ann Scherr, 1963-1985 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1960-1999 (Box 2, Folder 26-30)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 31)